Hello and welcome to this video in which we
will look at an example standard operating
procedure, or as it's more commonly called an SOP.
Previously you learned about workplace audits.
Following an audit, a standard
operating procedure can be created.
So what exactly is a standard operating procedure?
This is a document that outlines the steps
required to complete a specific task or process.
SOPs are used to ensure consistency and
quality in work processes, as well as
compliance with regulations and standards.
So let's take a look at an example
standard operating procedure document.
The one that you can see on the screen is a
Standard Operating Procedure, or SOP, and it
is for the organisation Creative Cooks, it's
for the restaurant department, and it has the
area or activity that this SOP relates to.
So in this instance, it's relating to the kitchen
and specifically to the kitchen staff responsible
for burger preparation in the fast food section.
So any other area or any other activity
that is undertaken would also have
a standard operating procedure.
It then goes on to give an indication of the PPE
required for the task or the area of operation.
There is also a space for any additional
safety information or precautions required.
You then come to the main body of the SOP.
The way to think about this section
is that it should cover all the steps
required for the preparation of a burger.
It is critical that it has to include every single
step involved in the preparation of that burger.
So as you can see in step one, we
have ingredients and supplies, and
there are three subtasks within that.
So you can see that this goes into quite
a lot of detail, such as checking that all
ingredients and supplies necessary for burger
preparation are stocked and readily available.
Checking the ingredient, freshness, and
getting rid of any expired or spoil items.
Maintaining the proper storage conditions for the
ingredients, such as refrigeration, is required.
You then go on to sanitisation and
personal hygiene, which has three
more elements in relation to that.
We then have the assembly lineup.
So this is about organising the workstation in
an assembly line manner to facilitate efficient
burger assembly, then burger preparation.
So how you would actually prepare the burger?
Then toasting the buns, the different
condiments and toppings, then the assembly of
the bun, packaging and presentation, quality
checks, the cleaning and maintenance, training
and communication, and finally, compliance
in relation to food safety, sanitisation
regulations, proper food handling, storage
and cooking temperatures, and all the
policies and procedures related to that.
So, as you can see, this is quite a
detailed document for what would seem
to be quite a straightforward task,
which is the preparation of a burger.
In your assessment, you will be required
to suggest what would be included in a SOP.
You may use the example in this video
to help you understand what information
might be needed for other tasks, such
as cleaning and tidying the office.
So what you need to think about is identifying
and listing all the different steps, so that
any member of staff will be able to use it as a
set of instructions, and carry out the measures
required to ensure that the workplace is kept
tidy and clean, and there's a place for everything
which will result in greater efficiency.
And a safer, productive and
pleasant working environment.
You can download a copy of this SOP to give you
an idea of the types of things that you should
be looking for and how much detail that you
should be going into when creating your SOP.